Inventory of the Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (I) 1780-1929
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Group C: John Thompson Brown Papers, 1816-1839., 6 boxes. (Box 14-19)
  - Box 14 - Papers of John Thompson Brown, son of Capt. Henry Brown; attendance at New London Academy; of his schooling at Princeton (1817-1820); his travels to the West Indies; his legal training under Judge Creed Taylor; arid his trip to Clarksburg, where he set up practice. Also bound scrapbook 
    - Report of John Thompson Brown of the senior class of Princeton; to [Henry Brown], 11 April 1820. (Box-folder 14:15)
    - Dr. William B. Steptoe, New London, to John Thompson Brown, 29 July 1820. (Box-folder 14:16)
      A 4th of July oration supporting the idea of colonizing the free Negroes in Africa.
    - Travel book kept by John Thompson Brown on his trip to the South, January [1821]., 15 pages. AD. (Box-folder 14:17)
    - John Thompson Brown, New Orleans, to his brother, Henry Brown, Jr., 14 January 1821. (Box-folder 14:18)
      "My father may justly complain of the great sums which he has expended on me, but his kindness shall not be abused much longer, as I hope to be in a situation to support myself." Endorsed: "Brother J.--after his return from Princeton went South--through the Cherokee Nation [Alabama and Georgia] to Pensacola, and on to New Orleans--thence to Cuba and returned to U. States in the U.S. Frigate 'Hornet,' as a guest of the officers. Samuel T. Brown."
    - John Thompson Brown, Lynchburg, to Henry Brown, 27 May 1823. (Box-folder 14:19)
      A gambling scrape he was involved in; asks his father's forgiveness.
    - John Thompson Brown, Needham, to Henry Brown, 10 November 1823. (Box-folder 14:20)
      "Chancellor Taylor has been of incalculable service to me in the study of law." (Needham was a law school operated by Judge Creed Taylor in Cumberland County in the years 1821-1836.)
    - [John Thompson Brown,] Lynchburg, to Peronneau [Finley]; continued, July 8, 1831, Petersburg, 25 April 1822. (Box-folder 14:21)
      These are the continuous drafts of a multiple of letters. The first section consists of musings and youthful recollections; the second is a humorous report on a 4th of July oration made in Petersburg after his marriage.
    - Alex. M. Jackson, at New London, to John Thompson Brown, "Student in the Law School, near Farmville," 24 July 1823. (Box-folder 14:22)
      Regarding the marriage of Dr. Steptoe.
    - John Thompson Brown's notes made at Judge Taylor's Law School, n.d. (Box-folder 14:23)
    - License of John Thompson Brown to practice law in the superior and inferior courts of this Commonwealth (Virginia), 7 March 1824. (Box-folder 14:24)
    - [John Thompson Brown], Otter Hills, to P. Finley, 20 May 1824. (Box-folder 14:25)
      Musings on Friendship and the wise behavior of a lawyer if he is to succeed.
    - [Judge] C[reed] Taylor, Lynchburg, to [Henry] St. George Tucker, at Winchester, 23 May 1824. (Box-folder 14:26)
      A letter introducing John Thompson Brown when he went to Clarksburg to set up practice.
    - John Thompson Brown's notebook, [June-November] 1824., 44 pages. (Box-folder 14:27)
      Musings written on a trip through Virginia: thoughts on a disappointing love affair; notes on "Crab Orchard" and the "Creek Nation" --the latter were to be incorporated into an Independence Day address delivered in Petersburg in 1831.
    - John Thompson Brown, Clarksburg, to Henry Brown, June-December 1824., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 14:28)
      Impressions of Clarksburg; the countryside is beautiful and the land very rich, but "The people have no money and are wretchedly poor and lazy..."
    - John Thompson Brown, Clarksburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., 20 August 1824. (Box-folder 14:29)
      His plans to establish himself.
    - Published Writings And Speeches Of John Thompson Brown, 1825-1832. (Box-folder 14:30)
      The following newspaper clippings and pamphlets are included in a bound scrap book, with endorsements and were undoubtedly collected by John Thompson Brown himself.
      - For the Clarksburg Intelligencer, Crawford and Adams, signed "Paul," [1825]. (Box-folder 14:30)
      - For the Clarksburg Intelligencer, signed "Jacob," n.d. (Box-folder 14:30)
        Concerning "several cases of contempt of court, occurring in various parts of the Union, in which the punishment inflicted, has been made a subject of grievous complaint."
      - For the Intelligencer, signed "Alexander," n.d. (Box-folder 14:30)
        Concerning "...Mr. Jefferson...the disclosure of his poverty..."
      - Clarksburg, Virginia For the Intelligencer, signed "Phocion," 17 December 1825. (Box-folder 14:30)
        Concerning "The President's message."
      - Report of a committee, Appointed to enquire into the nature and extent of the evils arising from the present unsettled state of Land Titles on the Western Waters of Virginia, 1827-1828. (Box-folder 14:30)
      - Virginia Legislature, Speech of Mr. Brown, of Harrison, in Committee of the Whole, Jan. 13th, Saturday, 31 January 1829. (Box-folder 14:30)
      - Virginia Legislature, 12 January 1830. (Box-folder 14:30)
        A Bill authorizing a loan of $6,000.00 on the credit of the state, for the construction of Turnpike Road from Winchester to Parkersburg by way of Clarksburg, being under consideration.
      - To "A Voter," 10 August 1831. (Box-folder 14:30)
        "Sir:--I have read in the "Intelligencer" of the 9th inst. your communications to the Editors of the paper, in which you remark, substantially, that the only Candidate to represent the town of Petersburg in the General Assembly is a stranger to most voters...Not doubting that I am the person alluded to...," signed John Thompson Brown"
      - Petersburg. Slave Mechanics, 8 November 1831. (Box-folder 14:30)
        "The following copy of a Petition to the Legislature of Virginia, we insert at the request of a number of our Citizens."
      - House of Delegates of Virginia, 11-18 January 1832., 32 pages. (Box-folder 14:30)
        "On motion of Mr. Brown of Petersburg, the report of the committee on slaves, free Negroes and mulattoes, and the amendment of Mr. Preston were taken up; when Mr. Brown rose and addressed the house as follows:..."
      - Virginia Legislature. House of Delegates. Petersburg Railroad, 13 February 1832. (Box-folder 14:30)
        "The bill to amend an act authorizing the Board of Public Works to subscribe on behalf of the Commonwealth, to the stock of the Petersburg Rail Road, was read a third time. Mr. Brown said..."
      - The Caucus, 15 March 1832. (Box-folder 14:30)
        "Andrew Jackson was unanimously recommended to the Citizens of Virginia, as the next President. "Mr. Miller of Powhatan then submitted the following Resolution..."(Concerning the Vice-President). Mr. Brown of Petersburg, then submitted the following by way of substitute for the above..."
  - Box 15 - Correspondence of John Thompson Brown while establishing himself in Clarksburg, and while representing Harrison County in the General Assembly, 1825-1829., 66 items. (Box-folder 15:1-39)
    The material in this box covers the period 1825 to 1829, when John Thompson Brown was resident of Clarksburg, Harrison County, Virginia (later West Virginia). In this period John Thompson Brown wrote some of the "Letters to the Editor," printed in the Clarksburg Enquirer, contained in the scrap book noted above in Box 14. A draft of a part of the letter concerning the poverty of Mr. Jefferson is to be found in this box (1825).
    In July 1826, John Thompson Brown wrote to his brother Henry Brown, Jr. of his aim to run for the U.S. Congress. In 1827 he was elected to the House of Delegates; he was re-elected in 1828 and 1829. This box also contains various printed and manuscript material touching upon his career in the General Assembly.
    By the end of 1829, John Thompson Brown had established himself in Clarksburg, built a house, and planned to buy into a partnership in a store to advance his financial position. In a letter of March 23, 1829 he mentions his desire to run in the next election for the U.S. Congress.
    - Henry Brown, Jr., New London, to his brother, John Thompson Brown, 20 February 1825. (Box-folder 15:1)
      "...the friends of Old Hickory...hear Adamses success spoken of and the probability of Clay's being made Secretary of State..."
    - John Thompson Brown, Clarksburg, to his father, Henry Brown, 2 September 1825. (Box-folder 15:2)
      Encloses a legal opinion concerning sheriffs, which his father apparently requested.
    - John Thompson Brown, Clarksburg, to Wm. P[eronneau] Finley, Charlestown, South Carolina, 20 December 1825. (Box-folder 15:3)
      A flowery letter to an old friend from Princeton. "I have acquired some little reputation at the bar and a practice that supports me very decently."
    - John Thompson Brown. "Mon Debut," [1825]. (Box-folder 15:4)
      Draft of an address to an investigating group (perhaps a grand jury), with endorsement: "1. Act against cutting down trees. 2. Act providing for a good and sufficient jail."
    - Draft of a letter to the editor, [1825]. (Box-folder 15:5)
      This is part of a printed letter concerning "Mr. Jefferson the disclosure of his poverty..." over the signature Alexander. (See bound scrapbook, the last item in Box 14.)
    - Henry Brown, Jr., Woodlawn, to Henry Brown, 10 July 1826. (Box-folder 15:6)
      Desire of John Thompson Brown to run for the U.S. Congress or for a seat in the General Assembly. Suggests that Henry Brown send $1,000.00 to help achieve this.
    - John Thompson Brown, Clarksburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., 8 November 1826. (Box-folder 15:7)
      "I find that there is a serious and, I believe, a somewhat general wish to bring me out for the Legislature."
    - John Thompson Brown, Clarksburg, to Henry Brown, 15 December 1826. (Box-folder 15:8)
      "I am a candidate for the Legislature at the next election..."
    - John Thompson Brown. "To the People of Harrison County," 9 February 1827. (Box-folder 15:9)
      An announcement of the candidacy of John Thompson Brown for the General Assembly. He reviews what he considers to be the most important problems of the day, and discusses (1) the invasion of State sovereignty by the Federal program of "internal development," (2) the harm done to Southern farmers by import duties, (3) the calling of a Constitutional Convention for the state of Virginia, (4) the dangers of the uncontrolled banking system.
    - John Thompson Brown, Clarksburg and Richmond, to Capt. Henry Brown, April-December 1827., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 15:10)
      His election to the General Assembly; hope of election to the U.S. Congress, and the purchase of a four acre lot in town. In the first letter which John Thompson Brown wrote from the House of Delegates he said "I have not taken much part in the debates of the House and do not expect to do so..."
    - Note regarding a report in the Richmond Enquirer "in regard to the question whether Clinton or Calhoun should run as Vice-President on the Jackson ticket," 25 September 1827. (Box-folder 15:11)
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to Henry Brown, Jr., 9 December 1827. (Box-folder 15:12)
      His ride to Richmond in a coach with other, more experienced law-makers, "having been, as you predicted, greatly edified and instructed by a coach-full of legislators 'big with the cares of state."
    - Report Of A Committee, Appointed To Enquire Into The Nature And Extent Of The Evils Arising From The Present Unsettled State Of Land Titles On The Western Waters Of Virginia, And To Devise A Remedy Therefor, With Leave To Report A Bill Or Otherwise, [1827-1828]., 6 pages. 2 copies. (Box-folder 15:13)
    - A Bill, For Settling And Adjusting The Titles Of Lands On The Western Waters Of Virginia, [1827-1828]., 3 copies. (Box-folder 15:14)
    - Draft of a petition of Anne Quinlin to the General Assembly for a divorce, [1827]. (Box-folder 15:15)
    - Draft of a petition of Edith Cornwall, [1827]. (Box-folder 15:16)
    - Drawing of a two room house, [1827-1830]. (Box-folder 15:17)
    - House plans and draft of explanations of a plan, [1827-1830]., 4 items. AD. (Box-folder 15:18)
    - House plan, elevations, and draft of notes on construction, [1825-1830]., 4 items. AD. (Box-folder 15:19)
    - R. H. Toler, Secretary, Lynchburg Colonization Society, to John Thompson Brown, 1 January 1828. (Box-folder 15:20)
      "Resolving that members of the House of Delegates be requested to unite...in advancing the cause of this Society before the General Assembly of Virginia."
    - Henry Brown, Jr., in Lynchburg, to Henry Brown, 5 February 1828. (Box-folder 15:21)
      On John Thompson Brown's speech: "considered the most able one that had been delivered in the House in 5 years."
    - R. R. Gurley, Colonization Society of Washington, to John Thompson Brown, 19 February 1828. (Box-folder 15:22)
      "Our Society, in the success of which, you are pleased to express so deep an interest, is I believe, making sure progress."
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to William Peronneau Finley, 1 March 1828. (Box-folder 15:23)
      His legislature activities and speeches. "I am a Jackson man like yourself but not perfectly orthodox, as you would say, on the subject of States Rights. I published my opinions, pamphlet of 30 pages, 12 months ago and will send you a copy..."
    - John Tho. Brown To The People Of Harrison [County], n.d., 17 pages. (Box-folder 15:24)
      A report to his constituents on such matters as (1) the state Constitutional Convention, (2) the lottery for the Randolph Academy in Clarksburg, (3) county elections, (4) the bill abolishing the chancery Courts and establishing a Superior Court, (5) a Turnpike to their area (defeated by the "Eastern People"), (6) the proposed Baltimore Railroad and (7) the settling of the question of land titles in Western Virginia. Included in the pamphlet are the full texts of the report of the committee on this subject, which he chaired, and the bill proposed by the committee.
    - Henry St. George Tucker, Winchester, to John Thompson Brown, 12 March 1828. (Box-folder 15:25)
      Comment on the land titles, Chancery court bills.
    - John Thompson Brown at Clarksburg and Sweet Springs, to Henry Brown, March-September 1828., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 15:26)
      "Even now I am as comfortably situated as I could desire and shall support myself hereafter without any further drafts on your goodness..."
    - John Thompson Brown, Clarksburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., May-July 1828., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 15:27)
      Now well situated in his "mansion," he discusses his prospects for Congress and of his plan to "offer 2 years hence."
    - Draft of a 4th of July speech, [4 July] 1828. (Box-folder 15:28)
    - Announcement of a meeting of the Alumni Association of Nassau Hall (Princeton), 14 August 1828. (Box-folder 15:29)
    - Regimental Order appointing John Thompson Brown Adjutant of the 11th Regiment, Virginia Militia, 9 October 1828. (Box-folder 15:30)
    - Muster Roll of the 11th Regiment, [1828]. (Box-folder 15:31)
    - "Notes...relating to Military Tactics...," [1828]., 5 items. AD. (Box-folder 15:32)
    - Military notes initialed "J. T. B.'s" [John Thompson Brown], [1828]., 2 items. AD. (Box-folder 15:33)
    - Military Notes, [1828]. (Box-folder 15:34)
      Endorsed: "McConley's System of Sword Tactics."
    - John Thompson Brown, Clarksburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., October 1828. (Box-folder 15:35)
      Reflections on people met at the Medicinal Springs, as contrasted with those of his constituency.
    - Wm. B. Giles. Report on the Board of Public Works, 23 January 1829. (Box-folder 15:36)
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to Henry Brown, February-December 1829., 8 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 15:37)
      In February, he forwards a copy of sheriff's commission to his father. During the year he borrows $400.00 for payments on his house in Clarksburg, and by the end of the year his father has agreed to advance enough capital for him to become a partner in a mercantile business. Upon the conclusion of the 1828-1829 session of the General Assembly, he writes that he will be a candidate once more, then run for Congress. In the letter of March 23rd, he writes that opposition has arisen "on account of some laws we had passed last session authorizing the county court to levy a tax for repairing roads and, bridges." On March 23rd he relates his experiences in Washington at the inauguration of Jackson: on December 14th he predicts that the basis of votes for whites will be surrendered in the formation of the new State constitution.
    - J[ames] M[urray] Mason, Winchester, to John Thompson Brown, 24 September 1829. (Box-folder 15:38)
      Suggests they ride together to Alexandria, then go to Richmond by boat.
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to Henry Brown, Jr., 6 December 1829. (Box-folder 15:39)
      The Virginia Constitutional Convention: "I had an opportunity of hearing the most distinguished members of the body--Mr. Madison and Mr. Marshall among the rest..."
  - Box 16 - Correspondence of John Thompson Brown after his marriage to Mary E. Willcox, of Petersburg (May 1830), and his move to that city, which he represented in the General Assembly in 1831. Also includes over one hundred toasts given at various occasions, 1829-1835, n.d., 85 items. (Box-folder 16:1-28u)
    The change which was to occur in the life and fortunes of John Thompson Brown in the year 1830 is forecast in the first letter of this box, a letter received by Mary E. Willcox of Petersburg in [December] 1829, in which there is a discussion of "Mr. B." Three months later (18 March 1830) in a letter to his father, John Thompson Brown announces his intention of leaving Clarksburg, and of his need for a horse and sulky so that he may arrive in Petersburg in a manner which should "avoid the appearance of poverty and destitution." The next letter in the collection (9 [May] 1830), in draft, contains an account of his wedding, a wedding which was attended by no members of his immediate family.
    Subsequent letters tell of the generosity of the new father-in-law John V. Willcox in the gift of a town house "provided with servants," a draft of $1500, and the promise of as much more as he asks (22 July 1830). Yet the position is not satisfactory and because John Thompson Brown feels that he is losing his independence, he returns to Clarksburg with the intention of resettling there and sending for his wife (2 May 1831). During a four week visit to Harrison County, he finds his political position has declined (7 June 1831), so he returns to Petersburg, and is invited to make the Independence Day address for the town (8 June 1831). As a result of this address (and the good influence of his father-in-law) he is nominated to represent the town in the House of Delegates, and is elected without opposition (26 September 1831).
    He successfully sponsors a bill in the Assembly for the Petersburg Railroad (28 December 1831), is appointed Judge of Elections for the Petersburg Office of the Bank of Virginia (29 December 1831), and is sought as a sponsor of a new newspaper which is being established in Richmond (20 October 1831). Of particular interest is a letter to his nephew outlining his philosophy of life and advising the young man on his future (3 October 1831). A report of the slave insurrection in Southhampton is described in a letter of 26 September 1831.
    At the end of this box are collected more than a hundred drafts of toasts made by John Thompson Brown.
    - G. Aell, Richmond, to Miss Mary E. Willcox, care of John V. Willcox, at Petersburg, 15 [December] 1829. (Box-folder 16:1)
      A friend writes regarding "Mr. B.," "a man of boundless pride and diffidence. His attachment was cut down in the bud and You, my sweetest Mary, have hoped whilst he desponded..."
    - List of names, cover addressed to Miss Mary E.Willcox, 27 October 1829. (Box-folder 16:2)
    - John Thompson Brown, Clarksburg, to Henry Brown, 18 March 1830. (Box-folder 16:3)
      "My friends, Webster, Goffard, and others believed I could certainly be elected to Congress next Spring...I wish to appear at P[etersburg] in a manner which would probably be expected and to avoid the appearance of poverty and destitution. Henry is to get me a sulky, horse, etc., and if you can spare this additional sum you may hand it over to him..."
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., 9 [May] 1830. (Box-folder 16:4)
      "Our nuptials took place at the time expected and I cannot say that there was any other allay to my happiness, than that neither you nor any of my near relatives were present."
    - John Thompson Brown, Washington City and Petersburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., May-June 1830., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 16:5)
      On his honeymoon: "Peronneau Finley travels with us, as one of our immediate party. Mr. Willcox, Sr., and three of his friends are going to N. York to the races. They came with us thus far..." There is much discussion about where they will live, but, "I think it probable we shall reside in Petersburg..."
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Henry Brown, 5 June 1830. (Box-folder 16:6)
      On his Washington visit: "we remained a week, were introduced to the President, etc., heard some interesting debates and saw all the great men of the nation...My situation is in all respects agreeable."
    - M. H. Garnett to Mrs. Mary E. Brown, 8 June 1830. (Box-folder 16:7)
      Congratulations on her marriage coupled with much advice.
    - John Thompson Brown, Lynchburg, to Henry Brown, July-December 1830., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 16:8)
      After a visit with his father, he writes: "I have nothing to add on the subject of my future arrangements. I shall pursue the course which you seemed to approve when we were together." He writes later that Mr. Willcox has turned over to them his town house "furnished with servants"; in another letter: "He handed me a check for $1,500 and said that I should always have as much as I wanted..."
    - John Thompson Brown, Walnut Hill in Petersburg, to Samuel T. Brown, 15 September 1830. (Box-folder 16:9)
      Sends advice to his younger brother and, and account of his own situation.
    - John Thompson Brown, Walnut Hill and Clarksburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., September-October 1830., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 16:10)
      Letters from Harrison County report that "the District needs me badly...but it is too late..."
    - Thomas W. Grimes, Charlottesville, to John Thompson Brown, 12 November 1830. (Box-folder 16:11)
      "I regret that you have temporarily declined public life--for I would not believe you have abondoned it altogether."
    - Notes on the case, Mclndoe vs. Dugger and Co., [1830]. (Box-folder 16:12)
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to his nephew, Edward Jenner Steptoe, February 1831., 2 items. ADr and ALS. (Box-folder 16:13)
      Advice given to a young man summarizing John Thompson Brown's own philosophy of life.
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Henry Brown, May-June 1831., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 16:14)
      On his return to Harrison County, "I found that my position here was to be too dependent..."
    - Thomas L. Wilson to John Thompson Brown, 8 June 1831. (Box-folder 16:15)
      "At a meeting of the citizens of Petersburg...'Resolved, that John Thompson Brown, Esq., he appointed Orator of the Day'."
    - John Thompson Brown. Drafts of Independence Day Address, 4 July 1831., 2 items. ADr. (Box-folder 16:16)
      The first important public speech of John Thompson Brown, in Petersburg, one which appears to have established his reputation, and which influenced his decision to remain there.